<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Keene 1617 an almanacke and prognostication for the yeare of our Lord God, 1617 : being the first yeare after the bissextile or leape yeare, the 35 from the reformed computation, and from the beginning of the world 5579 : composed properly for the latitude and meridian of London, and may well serue for the south part of Great Brittaine / by Iohn Keene ...</title>
            <author>Keene, John, fl. 1612-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 468.6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3228</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33143199</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33143199</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26629</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18034)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26629)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1826:12 or 1862:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Keene 1617 an almanacke and prognostication for the yeare of our Lord God, 1617 : being the first yeare after the bissextile or leape yeare, the 35 from the reformed computation, and from the beginning of the world 5579 : composed properly for the latitude and meridian of London, and may well serue for the south part of Great Brittaine / by Iohn Keene ...</title>
                  <author>Keene, John, fl. 1612-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38] p. ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For the Company of Stationers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1617]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title printed within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Second part has special t.p. with title: Keene 1617, a prognostication for this yeere of grace, 1617.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: copy at reel 1862, tightly bound, with slight loss of text; copy at reel 1826 a fragment consisting of C2-3 only.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]-B⁸, C³.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Cambridge University Library (reel 1826) and Lambeth Palace Library (London, England) (reel 1862).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Almanacs, English.</term>
               <term>Ephemerides.</term>
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="fragmentary_text">
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:26629:1"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
               <pb facs="tcp:26629:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
               <head>Of the Sommer time.</head>
               <p>ALl Globes (according to the Axiome) whoſe Axio<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Prouolution are paralell in one obliquely one to another: ſo our or be Axis, inclining to the Spheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body of light, prouolueth ſurface to ſurface with obliquation and paralax, and now beeing the xi of Iune in the neareſt poynt of inclination, ſhewes eury part of his ſuperficies to the Sunnes view, with greateſt ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualitic and differance; and conſequently this his inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to greateſt ſhew of Sunſhine, and leaſt ſhadow on the Sunne (after the receaue oft opinion) in the greateſt Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly declination, making with vs, longeſt day and ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt night: which eyther way taken, are vſually receiued for the third part of the Aſtronomicall yeare, Ifind that will be much diſpoſed to heate and drought, (not much different from his naturall inclination) and it will be much diſpoſed to thunder, not much differing from the diſpoſe of Summer 1616. The Infirmities are like to be Sweatings, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumes, Inflammations, Hecticke, Agues, and other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities proceeding of Choller.</p>
               <p>In this Seaſon we muſt eate little and often. (as <hi>Galen</hi> teacheth) becauſe we neede more often Nouriſhing, and Drinke more abundantly Wine, being qualified.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:26629:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
               <head>Of Autumne.</head>
               <p>ANy two Orbs hauing their motion in a perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculer line one to another, including both their Axis obiect Plane to Plane, directly each to other: but our darke obſcure opacous, and ſphearicall Orbe (the xii. of September) prouoluing himſelfe in ſuch a habitude to the Globe of Lights conuere, obiecteth each por<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of his plane in equall plane, to equall elumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and ſo maketh day and night alike-long all this world ouer. The moment of which habitude, giueth the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to the laſt quarter of the Aſtronomicall yeare cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <hi>Autumne</hi> or Harueſt.</p>
               <p>The Dyſcraſit of this time of the yeare, is the cauſe of many Diſeaſes, and will be now the occaſion of Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Strangurie, Goutes, Collicke, and Illiacke paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Dropſies; beſides many other Phlegmaticke griefes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="regnal_table">
               <pb facs="tcp:26629:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> compendious Table for <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>criuener<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>; ſuch as are imployed in Law cauſes.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> number of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> &amp; Queenes.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">The names of the Kings of England.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">The begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their Reignes.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">The time of their deaths.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Anno Domini</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>William <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>onqu.</cell>
                        <cell>October. 14.</cell>
                        <cell>September. 9.</cell>
                        <cell>1087</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>William Rufus.</cell>
                        <cell>September. 9.</cell>
                        <cell>Auguſt. 1.</cell>
                        <cell>1100</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>Henry the 1.</cell>
                        <cell>Auguſt. 1.</cell>
                        <cell>December. 2.</cell>
                        <cell>1136</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>Stephen</cell>
                        <cell>December. 2.</cell>
                        <cell>October. 25.</cell>
                        <cell>1154</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>Henry the 2.</cell>
                        <cell>October. 25.</cell>
                        <cell>Iuly. 6.</cell>
                        <cell>1189</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>Richard the 1.</cell>
                        <cell>Iuly. 6.</cell>
                        <cell>Aprill. 6.</cell>
                        <cell>1199</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>Iohn.</cell>
                        <cell>Aprill. 6.</cell>
                        <cell>October. 19.</cell>
                        <cell>1216</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>Henry the 3.</cell>
                        <cell>October. 19.</cell>
                        <cell>Nouemb. 16.</cell>
                        <cell>1227</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>Edward the 1.</cell>
                        <cell>Nouemb. 16.</cell>
                        <cell>Iuly. 6.</cell>
                        <cell>1307</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>Edward the 2.</cell>
                        <cell>Iuly. 6.</cell>
                        <cell>Ianuary. 25</cell>
                        <cell>1327</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>Edward the 3.</cell>
                        <cell>Ianuary. 25.</cell>
                        <cell>Iune. 21.</cell>
                        <cell>1377</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>Richard the 2.</cell>
                        <cell>Iune. 21.</cell>
                        <cell>Septemb. 16.</cell>
                        <cell>1400</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>Henry the 4.</cell>
                        <cell>Septemb. 16.</cell>
                        <cell>March. 20.</cell>
                        <cell>1413</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>Henry the 5.</cell>
                        <cell>March. 20.</cell>
                        <cell>Auguſt. 31.</cell>
                        <cell>1422</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>Henry the 6.</cell>
                        <cell>Auguſt. 31.</cell>
                        <cell>March. 4.</cell>
                        <cell>1461</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>Edward the 4.</cell>
                        <cell>March 4.</cell>
                        <cell>Aprill. 9.</cell>
                        <cell>1483</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>Edward the 5.</cell>
                        <cell>Aprill. 9.</cell>
                        <cell>Iune. 22.</cell>
                        <cell>1484</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>Richard the 3.</cell>
                        <cell>Iune. 22.</cell>
                        <cell>Auguſt. 22.</cell>
                        <cell>1486</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>Henry the 7.</cell>
                        <cell>Auguſt. 22.</cell>
                        <cell>Aprill. 22.</cell>
                        <cell>150<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>Henry the 8.</cell>
                        <cell>Aprill. 22.</cell>
                        <cell>Ianuary. 28.</cell>
                        <cell>1547</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>Edward the 6.</cell>
                        <cell>Ianuary. 28.</cell>
                        <cell>Iuly. 6.</cell>
                        <cell>155<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>Queene Mary.</cell>
                        <cell>Iuly 6.</cell>
                        <cell>Nouemb. 17.</cell>
                        <cell>1519</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>Queene Elizab.</cell>
                        <cell>Nouemb. 17.</cell>
                        <cell>March. 24.</cell>
                        <cell>1603</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>King Iames.</cell>
                        <cell>March. 24.</cell>
                        <cell>Long <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iue</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:26629:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
               <head>Obſeruations Aſtronomic<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll fo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is yeare .1617.</head>
               <p>THe true quantitie of the Tropicall yeare 365 dayes 5. howers. 49. minuts.</p>
               <p>The true Preceſſion of the Equinoxies, 28. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, 30. minuts, 40. ſeconds.</p>
               <p>The greateſt obliquity of the Zodiacke, is 23. degrees, 31. minuts, 30. ſeconds.</p>
               <p>The Eccentricity of the Sunne 3502. ſuch parts, as the Semidiameter of the Excentricke is 100000, or two parts, 9. minuts, ſuch as the Semidiameter is 60. parts.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Sanctae Trinitati ſit gloria.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:26629:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
